<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Johnny's Journey</title><link href="johnnysjourneys.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="johnnysjourneys.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>johnnysjourneys.com/</id><updated>2016-01-03T02:55:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>The Journey Begins</title><link href="johnnysjourneys.com/the-journey-begins.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-01-03T02:55:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Jonathan Colon</name></author><id>tag:,2016-01-03:johnnysjourneys.com/the-journey-begins.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Where Do I Begin?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name is Jonathan Colon, and over the past year or so I have been developing in Python.
I love developing in Python, and just programming in general. That is why I have made it my mission
to learn more languages, mainly C and Clojure. I could never have done any of this without the support of
the &lt;strong&gt;CodeNewbie&lt;/strong&gt; community. They have helped me so much, and have been such an inspiration on my journey.
I am proud to say I am a part of the CodeNewbie community. I am also proud to say I am part of the
&lt;strong&gt;#Python_Thursday&lt;/strong&gt; crew. Together, we have inspired countless projects and helped even more Newbies realize
they have the chops to become a developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;New Year, New Language&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have decided to learn Clojure in 2016, as well as, continue learning C and Python.
Let's face it though, every developer knows you never truly stop learning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may be wondering why I chose to learn Clojure. Well, I have always been fascinated with Artificial Intelligence
and when you do research Lisp always seems to pop up. Since this keyword kept coming up in my research
I decided to look more into Lisp, and found that it is considered a &lt;em&gt;family of functional programming languages&lt;/em&gt;. Clojure is part of the Lisp family. Some members of the &lt;strong&gt;#Python_Thursday&lt;/strong&gt; crew decided to take up this challenge for the new year
as well. Together we know we will learn all that functional programming has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Follow Me On My Journey!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now to the really exciting news! I am going to be writing weekly posts in regards to my journey learning Clojure, as well as,
posts updating my followers on my Python/C journey as well. As I said earlier, you never truly stop learning, so there
will always be new posts. The other goal of these posts is to show every developer, both new and old, that coding can be
challenging at times and you really just need to keep at it. You will find the solution to your problem with time and when
that time comes you will feel better than you ever have. Why? Because you did it, you were able to overcome that hurdle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope these posts inspire you to never give up and keep pushing ahead. See you all in the next post!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>